Chase Stokes

<u>cstokes@ischool.berkeley.edu</u> <u>chasejstokes.github.io</u>

I am a mixed methods researcher situated at the intersection of language and visualization. My work focuses on the challenges and opportunities presented by multimodal information displays, delving into how language shapes the reader's experience and understanding. I aim to identify best practices for integrating text and visualizations and improve the effectiveness of information communication.

EDUCATION

PhD. in Information Science

2021 – present

University of California at Berkeley

Advisor: Marti Hearst, PhD.

Relevant coursework: HCI Research, UX Research, Information

Visualization and Presentation, Interface Aesthetics

B.A. in Psychology and Gender and Sexuality Studies

2021

Northwestern University, GPA 3.92 Advisor: Steven Franconeri, PhD.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Graduate Student Researcher

2021 – present

Hearst Lab, UC Berkeley

Temporary Research Assistant

Summer 2024

Northeastern University, Khoury College

Research Intern

Summer 2023

Tableau

Undergraduate Research Assistant

2018 - 2021

Visual Thinking Lab, Northwestern University

Data Collector Summer 2021

Couple and Family Development Lab, The Family Institute at Northwestern University

Undergraduate Research Assistant

2019 - 2021

Couple and Family Development Lab, The Family Institute at Northwestern University

Undergraduate Summer Intern

Summer 2019

Couple and Family Development Lab, The Family Institute at Northwestern University

PUBLICATIONS

- **Stokes, C.,** Sanker, C., Cogley, B., & Setlur, V. (2024). From Delays to Densities: Exploring Uncertainty through Speech, Text, and Visualization. Computer Graphics Forum.
- **Stokes, C.,** Sanker, C., Cogley, B., & Setlur, V. (2024). Mixing Modes: Active and Passive Integration of Speech, Text, and Visualization for Communicating Data Uncertainty. Computer Graphics Forum.
- **Stokes, C.,** Bearfield, C. X., & Hearst, M.A. (2023). The Role of Text in Visualizations: How Annotations Shape Perceptions of Bias and Influence Predictions. IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.
- Bearfield, C. X., **Stokes, C.,** Lovett, A., & Franconeri, S. (2023). What Does the Chart Say? Grouping Cues Guide Viewer Comparisons and Conclusions in Bar Charts. IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.
- **Stokes, C.,** Setlur, V., Cogley, B., Satyanarayan, A., and Hearst, M.A. (2022). Striking a Balance: Reader Takeaways and Preferences when Integrating Text and Charts. IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.
- Xiong, C., **Stokes, C.,** Kim, Y. S., & Franconeri, S. (2022). Seeing What You Believe or Believing What You See? Belief Biases Correlation Estimation. IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.

WORKSHOP PAPERS

- **Stokes, C.,** and Hearst, M.A. (2022). Why More Text is (Often) Better: Themes from Reader Preferences for Integration of Charts and Text, NLVIZ Workshop, IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.
- **Stokes, C.,** and Hearst, M.A. (2021). Give Text A Chance: Advocating for Equal Consideration for Language and Visualization, NLVIZ Workshop, IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics.

POSTERS AND PRESENTATIONS

- **Stokes, C.,** Xiong, C., & Hearst, M.A. (2022, Nov). Driving Reader Interpretations with Text Annotations in Data Visualizations. Poster presented at Society for Judgement and Decision Making, San Diego, CA.
- Xiong, C., **Stokes, C.,** Lovett, A., & Franconeri, S. (2021, May). Visual Salience and Grouping Cues Guide Relation Perception in Visual Data Displays. Poster presented at Virtual Vision Sciences Society.
- **Stokes, C.,** Xiong, C., & Franconeri, S. (2020, May). Seeing What You Want: Prior Belief Biases Perception of Correlation in Scatterplots. Poster presented at Virtual 32nd APS Annual Convention, Chicago, IL.
- Callahan, C., **Stokes, C.,** & Lawrence, E. (2020, May). Modifying the Relationship Quality Interview for Sexual and Gender Minority Couples. Accepted Poster Presentation at the 8th Annual LGBTQ Research Symposium at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign. (Conference Canceled)

FELLOWSHIPS, AWARDS, AND HONORS

· · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · · ·	
Fellowships	
NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program Recipient	2023 – present
Ford Foundation Predoctoral Fellowship Honorable Mention	2023
School of Information Fellowship for Doctoral Study	2021 – 2022
Awards	0047 0004
National Merit Finalist	2017 – 2021
Hamaya	
Honors Departmental Honors - Psychology	2021
Departmental Honors - Psychology Phi Beta Kappa	2021
Northwestern University Dean's List with Distinction	2017 – 2021
Northwestern onliversity Deart's List with Distinction	2017 - 2021
GRANTS	
Northwestern Summer Undergraduate Research Grant (\$3,500)	Summer 2020
Visual Grouping Affords Different Comparison Patterns in Visualized Data	3
3 - 1 - 1 - 1 - 1 - 1 - 1 - 1 - 1 - 1 -	
Northwestern Academic Year Research Grant (\$1,000)	2020
Variations in Conclusions Afforded by Chart Type	
STUDENT LEADERSHIP ROLES	
Underrepresented Applicant Feedback Program	2023
Co-coordinated initiative to provide feedback to underrepresented PhD. applicants	
	opiicants
NorCal Visualization Group Organizer	2022 – 2023
NorCal Visualization Group Organizer Organized 6 unique speakers for hour-long seminars	
Organized 6 unique speakers for hour-long seminars	2022 – 2023
Organized 6 unique speakers for hour-long seminars Trainings Chair	
Organized 6 unique speakers for hour-long seminars	2022 – 2023
Organized 6 unique speakers for hour-long seminars Trainings Chair Masculinity, Allyship, Reflection, and Solidarity (M.A.R.S.)	2022 – 2023 2019 – 2020
Organized 6 unique speakers for hour-long seminars Trainings Chair Masculinity, Allyship, Reflection, and Solidarity (M.A.R.S.) Participant Coordinator,	2022 - 2023 2019 - 2020 2019 - 2020
Organized 6 unique speakers for hour-long seminars Trainings Chair Masculinity, Allyship, Reflection, and Solidarity (M.A.R.S.) Participant Coordinator, Pre-Orientation Program Coordinator	2022 – 2023 2019 – 2020
Organized 6 unique speakers for hour-long seminars Trainings Chair Masculinity, Allyship, Reflection, and Solidarity (M.A.R.S.) Participant Coordinator,	2022 - 2023 2019 - 2020 2019 - 2020
Organized 6 unique speakers for hour-long seminars Trainings Chair Masculinity, Allyship, Reflection, and Solidarity (M.A.R.S.) Participant Coordinator, Pre-Orientation Program Coordinator	2022 - 2023 2019 - 2020 2019 - 2020
Organized 6 unique speakers for hour-long seminars Trainings Chair Masculinity, Allyship, Reflection, and Solidarity (M.A.R.S.) Participant Coordinator, Pre-Orientation Program Coordinator Alternative Student Breaks (A.S.B.)	2022 - 2023 2019 - 2020 2019 - 2020 2018 - 2019
Organized 6 unique speakers for hour-long seminars Trainings Chair Masculinity, Allyship, Reflection, and Solidarity (M.A.R.S.) Participant Coordinator, Pre-Orientation Program Coordinator Alternative Student Breaks (A.S.B.) Programming Committee	2022 - 2023 2019 - 2020 2019 - 2020 2018 - 2019
Organized 6 unique speakers for hour-long seminars Trainings Chair Masculinity, Allyship, Reflection, and Solidarity (M.A.R.S.) Participant Coordinator, Pre-Orientation Program Coordinator Alternative Student Breaks (A.S.B.) Programming Committee	2022 - 2023 2019 - 2020 2019 - 2020 2018 - 2019
Organized 6 unique speakers for hour-long seminars Trainings Chair Masculinity, Allyship, Reflection, and Solidarity (M.A.R.S.) Participant Coordinator, Pre-Orientation Program Coordinator Alternative Student Breaks (A.S.B.) Programming Committee Rainbow Alliance	2022 - 2023 2019 - 2020 2019 - 2020 2018 - 2019
Organized 6 unique speakers for hour-long seminars Trainings Chair Masculinity, Allyship, Reflection, and Solidarity (M.A.R.S.) Participant Coordinator, Pre-Orientation Program Coordinator Alternative Student Breaks (A.S.B.) Programming Committee Rainbow Alliance STUDENT MEMBERSHIPS	2022 - 2023 2019 - 2020 2019 - 2020 2018 - 2019 2018 - 2019
Organized 6 unique speakers for hour-long seminars Trainings Chair Masculinity, Allyship, Reflection, and Solidarity (M.A.R.S.) Participant Coordinator, Pre-Orientation Program Coordinator Alternative Student Breaks (A.S.B.) Programming Committee Rainbow Alliance STUDENT MEMBERSHIPS Association for Computing Machinery, Student Member Psychonomic Society, Student Member Cognitive Science Society, Student Member	2019 - 2020 2019 - 2020 2019 - 2020 2018 - 2019 2018 - 2019 2021 - present 2021 - present 2021 - present
Organized 6 unique speakers for hour-long seminars Trainings Chair Masculinity, Allyship, Reflection, and Solidarity (M.A.R.S.) Participant Coordinator, Pre-Orientation Program Coordinator Alternative Student Breaks (A.S.B.) Programming Committee Rainbow Alliance STUDENT MEMBERSHIPS Association for Computing Machinery, Student Member Psychonomic Society, Student Member	2022 - 2023 2019 - 2020 2019 - 2020 2018 - 2019 2018 - 2019 2021 - present 2021 - present

AD-HOC REVIEWS

Ocean and Coastal Research	2023
Journal of Official Statistics	2023
Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (TVCG)	2023 - 2024
ACM Computer-Human Interaction (CHI)	2022 - 2024
IEEE VIS Short Papers	2022
Creativity & Cognition	2021
SERVICE AND OUTREACH	
25th Anniversary of the Master of Information Management and Systems	2022
Facilitated two 30-minute panels	
	0000 0000
PhD. Applicant Feedback Program	2022 - 2023
Provided feedback to underrepresented applicants	
Student Volunteer at IEEE VIS	2022
Washington University School of Medicine	2019, 2021
Mini-Medical School Panelist	
Alternative Student Breaks	2017 – 2019
Allemative Student Dieaks	2017 - 2019
College Mentors for Kids	2017 – 2019

REFERENCES PROVIDED UPON REQUEST